Finding Aid of the UW-Milwaukee Urban Studies Programs, 1956-2011
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
UW-Milwaukee Urban Studies Programs, 1956-2011
UW-Milwaukee Urban Studies Programs
UWM Archival Collection 68
6.3 cubic ft. (9 boxes and 1 flat box)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Documents from Urban Studies Programs, formerly the Department of Urban Affairs. Included are documents relating to the establishment of the Department, meeting minutes, correspondence, program event materials, and academic planning documents, including proposals for a doctoral program and a Master of Public Administration. Much of the collection consists of records related to the Ford Foundation, which awarded the Department of Urban Affairs an early research grant. Syllabi files dating from 1981 to 2011, program reviews, and event posters are also included.
The Department of Urban Affairs was established in 1963 within the College of Letters and Science. In 1965 an Urban Studies Program was established within the Department of Urban Affairs for undergraduates participating in the following majors: economics, geography, political science, and sociology. The Urban Planning program was established within the Department of Urban Affairs in Spring of 1975. The department was subsumed into Urban Studies Programs in 1987, although a separate Master of Science in Urban Affairs was still offered until 1993.
Department Chairs, Department of Urban Affairs
1963-1967 Henry J. Schmandt
1967-1970 Warner Bloomberg
1970-1973 Harold Rose
1973-1974 Henry J. Schmandt
1974-1977 Harold Rose
1977-1980 Richard Bingham
1980-1982 C. Nachmias
1982-1987 Michael Barndt
Directors of Urban Studies Programs
1987-1991 Frank Cassell
1991-1993 Marc Levine
1993-1995 William Huxhold
1995-1998 Dale Jaffe
1998-2000 Donald Noel
2001 Judith Kenny
2001-2005 Margo Anderson
2005-2008 Joseph Rodriquez
2008-2012 Amanda Seligman
2012-2015 Jasmine Alinder
2015- Joel Rast
The collection includes documents from the Urban Research Committee's proposals for the urban studies program, and an outline of a proposed 5-10 year urban studies department program. Also included are course proposals within the History Department and proposals for graduate program in urban studies. A large portion of the collection is comprised of records regarding the Ford Foundation, which awarded a research grant in December 1959.
Records of the Urban Studies Program itself include documents pertaining to the proposal for an Urban Affairs Department and for an urban studies program for undergraduates, a doctoral degree program, a joint degree program with the School of Education or the School of Information Studies, and master's of public administration program. Also included are minutes from the Department of Urban Affairs, which consist of various memos and announcements relating to courses, staffing, budgets and other departmental functions. Course syllabi, program reviews, and a flat box containing student recruitment and program event posters are also included. The collection also contains program brochures, several issues of the Intrapost, Urban Affair newspaper, and USI News.
This collection was received in, and is organized in, multiple parts. Additional materials have been physically or intellectually arranged and interfiled, and researchers may need to consult more than one part of the collection to locate similar materials.
UWM Archival Collection 68: Records, 1956-1984
The collection contains two additional accessions.
Accession 2010-065: Subject Files, 1962-2011
Accession 2011-027: Syllabi and Subject Files, 1981-2011
Administrative/Restriction Information
NEEDS RESTRICTION STATEMENT There are no access restrictions on the materials, and the collection is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
An unknown donor transferred the collection to the Archives prior to 1989. Accession 2010-065 was donated by an unknown donor in June 2011. The Urban Studies Program donated accession 2011-027 in December 2011.
Contents List
- Records, 1956-2011, UWM Archival Collection 68; 6.3 cubic ft. (9 boxes and 1 flat box)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Student Awards, Scott Greer Award, 1995-2003 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Ad Hoc Curriculum Committee, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Ad Hoc Review Committee for Urban Social Institutions, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Admissions Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - American Sociological Association, Graduate Department Surveys, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Restricted
  - Annual Poster Recruitment, 1996-2005 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Awards Committee, 2007-2008 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Center of Excellence Proposal, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Colloquiums, Memorandums, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Commendation from Governor Lee Sherman Dreyfus, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Committee Structure, 1999-2007 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Community Advisory Committee, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Community Development Work Study Grant Proposal (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Community Research Committee, 1980-1983 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence
    - 1977-1987 (Box 5, Folder 36-39)
    - 1982-1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1988-2004 (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
  - Correspondence, College of Letters & Science, 1967-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Dean of Letters & Science, 1960-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Ford Foundation, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Graduate School Administration, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 1966-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Correspondence, Outgoing from Chava Nachmias, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Outgoing from Harold M. Rose, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
  - Correspondence, Outgoing from Michael Barndt, 1980-1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Urban Studies Advisory Committee, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and Memorandums, 1976-2000 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Course and Curriculum Committee, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Course Descriptions, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Course Descriptions and Flyers, 2006-2010 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1982-2010 (Box 6, Folder 9-12)
  - Department of Housing and Urban Development, Community Development Work Study Program Grant Proposal, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Department of Urban Affairs Profile, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Development Committee, 2006-2007 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Dissertation List, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Doctor of Philosophy in Urban Social Institutions Proposal, 1972-1976 (Box 6, Folder 15-16)
  - Doctoral Graduate Exit Interviews, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Doctoral Program
    - Admissions, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Committee on Reviews, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1989-1996 (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
    - Faculty List Given to Students, 1981-1983 (Box 6, Folder 20-21)
    - First Draft of Program by Scott Greer, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Five Year Review, 1977-1983 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Memorandums, 1997-2005 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Program Array Review, 1997-2000 (Box 6, Folder 24-25)
    - Program Array Review Results, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Proposals and Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 27-28)
    - Report for Five Year Review, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Doctoral Studies Advisory Committee, 2002-2004 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Doctorate in Urban Social Institutions Handbook for Graduate Students, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Dual Masters Degree Program, Library Science and Urban Studies, 1983-1987 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - E-Journal Committee, 2006-2007 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Executive Committee of the Ford Foundation Urban Project, 1960-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee of the Ford Foundation Urban Project, 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Committee on Instruction and Training in Urban Studies, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Faculty List, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1981-1983 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes and Agenda, 1988-2007 (Box 6, Folder 36-38)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes and Correspondence, 1986-1997 (Box 5, Folder 12-14)
  - Fall Open House and Social, 2002-2006 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Ford Foundation Work Group, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ford Urban and Brittingham Fellowships, 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fox Valley Projects, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Graduate and Doctoral Program Brochures and Recruitment, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Graduate Certificate in Nonprofit Management, 2002-2003 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Graduate Faculty Council, Administrative Manual and Minutes, 2001-2005 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Graduate Program, Five Year Review, 1973-1987 (Box 7, Folder 4-6)
  - Graduate Program Name Change, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Graduate Program Planning, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Graduate Program Proposal, 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Graduate Program Review, 1987-2000 (Box 7, Folder 10-12)
  - Graduate Program Review, Two Year Follow Up, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Graduate Student Fairs, 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Graduate Student Placement and Employment, 2003-2007 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Graduate Students and Postdoctorates in Science and Engineering Survey, 1985-1996 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Grant and Program Proposals, 1996-2002 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Scott Greer Award Recipients, 2011 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Scott Greer Memorial, 1996-2000 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Grievance and Appeals Committee, 2010 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - History of and Proposals for Urban Affairs Department and Urban Studies, 1961-1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Institute of Urban and Regional Studies, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Institutional Grant and Fellowship Proposal, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Instructional Statistics, 1995-2002 (Box 7, Folder 19-20)
  - Internship Committee Meeting, Minutes, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Intrapost, July-September 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Joint Degree: Urban Affairs/Education, 1959-1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Knapp Visiting Professorship, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lectures and Programs, 1991-2006 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Lectures and Programs Committee, 1995-2009 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Henry Maier Fund, 1988-2002 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Henry Maier State of Milwaukee Summit, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Masters Program
    - Consultant's Report, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Five Year Review, 1987-1989 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Program Array Review, 1997-1999 (Box 7, Folder 27-28)
    - Program Repositioning Committee, 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Ten Year Review Report, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Memorandum, 1978-1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Merit Salary Committee, 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Mini-Review of Department of Urban Affairs, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Minutes, 1963-1977 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Minutes, 1978-1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters
    - 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - 2005-2006 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Posters and Brochures, 2007-2010 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Preliminary Examinations Committee, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Pro-Seminar, 1991-1995 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Program Brochures
    - 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1995 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Program Evaluations and Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Program Planning, 1981-2001 (Box 7, Folder 40-41)
  - Program Restructuring Proposals, 1982-1989 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Progress Reports to the Dean, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Progress Reports to the Ford Foundation, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Proposal for Doctoral Degree Program, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Proposal for Master's of Public Administration Program, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Proposals for Graduate Program in Urban Affairs, 1959-1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Research Training Program in Urban Transportation, Progress Reports, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Speaker and Colloquium Series, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Speaker Series, Gary Hoover, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Spring Newsletter, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Statistical Reports, 1996-1999 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Steering Committee, 1977-2011 (Box 8, Folder 4-10)
  - Student Affairs Committee, 1988-2010 (Box 5, Folder 18-20)
  - Student Committee, 2006-2007 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Student Forum
    - Eighth Annual, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Fifth Annual, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - First Annual, 1995-1996 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Fourth Annual, 1998-1999 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Ninth Annual, 2003-2004 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Second Annual, 1996-1997 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Seventh Annual, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Sixth Annual, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Tenth Annual, 2004-2005 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Tenth Annual, Paper Submissions, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 20-21)
    - Third Annual and Scott Greer Award, 1997-1999 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Twelth Annual, 2007 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Student Recruitment and Program Event Posters (Box 10)
  - Student Strike, May 1970 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Summer Institute, 1981-1983 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Syllabi
    - Course Numbers 250-971, 1981-2011 (Box 8, Folder 25-29)
    - Course Numbers 979-989, 1984-2010 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
  - Symposium on Milwaukee History, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Ten Year Academic Plan, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Undergranduate Certificate Brochures, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Urban Affair Newspaper, 1968-1975 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Urban Forum, 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Urban History Program, Course Proposals, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Urban Insight, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Urban Research Center, 1977-1982 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Urban Research Committee, 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Urban Transportation Institutional Grant Research and Training Proposals, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - USI News, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)